Guide to the Institute for Policy Studies Marcus Raskin files, 1959-2009 MS2349
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Institute for Policy Studies Marcus Raskin files
1959-2009
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Institute for Policy Studies
MS2349
6 Linear Feet
This collection contains handwritten and typed drafts, revised drafts, correspondence, syllabi, government papers, and personal papers. These materials represent the personal papers of Marcus Raskin, the materials he created and collected with the Institute for Policy Studies, as a professor at The George Washington University and his time working for the National Security Council. The materials date from 1959-2009.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: Governement papers, Speeches and publications and Correspondence and personal papers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Institute for Policy Studies, 2016 (2016.031)
Scope and Contents
This collection contains handwritten and typed drafts, revised drafts, correspondence, syllabi, government papers, and personal papers. The documents date between 1959 and 2009.
Biographical / Historical
Marcus Raskin (b. 1934- ) is the co-founder of the progressive think tank, the Institute for Policy Studies, located in Washington, DC and an author of numerous books and articles. In 1961 Harvard sociologist David Riesman recommended Raskin, a recent graduate of the University of Chicago Law School, to McGeorge Bundy, the National Security Advisor to the newly elected president, John F. Kennedy. Raskin served as Bundy's assistant on national security affairs and disarmament as a member of the Special Staff of the National Security Council.
In 1963, Raskin left government service and founded, with fellow government worker Richard Barnet, the Institute for Policy Studies (IPS). Much of Raskin's initial work with IPS focused on opposing the Vietnam War. He co-authored The Viet-nam Reader with Bernard Fall in 1965, which was used in dozens of teach-ins across the country.
Marcus Raskin is the author and co-author of more than twenty books and countless articles related to the progressive movement including topics such as as anti-war, liberalism, anti-nuclear movement, and pro-environment.
He is also a professor of public policy at The George Washington University's School of Public Policy and Public Administration.
Other Finding Aids
https://library.gwu.edu/ead/ms2297.xml. The Marcus Raskin papers
Public policy; Liberalism; Raskin, Marcus G.
- Government papers, 1959-2000; Series 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains documents from and related to Marcus Raskins years working for the United States Governement. The documents date between 1959-2009.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Documents Relating to the Liberal Papers Copy, 1959-1962; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - IPS Documents Copy, 1961-1963; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Government Papers, 1961-1963; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Nuclear History Documents Copy National Security Counsel, 1961-1963; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Foreign Policy Documents Copy National Security Council, 1961-1963; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Civil Defense Documents Copy, 1961-1962; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Domestic Affairs/Miscellaneous Documents Copy, 1961-1963; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Education Documents Copy, 1961-1963; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Government Papers, 1964-1966; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Marcus Raskin Memos to Bundy JFK Library, 1961; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - National Security Council Memo, 1961; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Disarmament, 1992; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Raskin Papers - Arms Control and Anti-Semi, 1993; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Center for National Security, 1995; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Hague Peace Appeal, 1999; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Kosovo, 1999; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Common Good Trust, 2000; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Speeches and publications, 1959-2004; Series 2
  This series contains drafts of speeches and publications by Marcus Raskin. The dates range from 1959-2004.
  - Liberalism in Dem Party, 1959; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Pathways to the 21st Century, 1971-2004; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Freedom Book, 1980-2006; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Health Navarro, 1988; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Term Papers, 1989-1990; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Raskin on Soviet Union, 1989; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Paths for 21st Century: 3 Year MacArthur, 1990; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 21st Century Proposal, 1991; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Affirmative Action, 1991; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Education Project, 1991; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Paths to the 21st Century, 1992; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Abolishing the War System, 1992; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Conference on Nuremberg, 1993; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - GW - National Security State, 1993; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Progressive Challenge, 1993; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Paths Budget, 1994-2004; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Paths Multi-Media T.V., 1994; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Paths Summaries, 1994; Series 2 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - NSS Seminar, 1994; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - NSS Seminar, 1994; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Nuremberg Conference - Background, 1994; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Paths Notes, 1994; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Visions and Revisions Last Drafts, 1994; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Marcus Raskin on Paramilitaries and Mercenaries, 1994; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Nuremberg/International Law, 1994; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 21st Century, 1995; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Paths Publishers, 1995; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - NSS and Domestic Reconstruction, 1996; Series 2 (Box BOX 6, Folder 1)
  - Presidential Disrespect Draft, 1997; Series 2 (Box BOX 6, Folder 2)
  - Presidential Disrespect, 1997; Series 2 (Box BOX 6, Folder 3)
  - Presidents Book 2 Drafts, 1997; Series 2 (Box BOX 6, Folder 4)
  - Presidents Book Drafts 1, 1997; Series 2 (Box BOX 6, Folder 5)
  - Presidential Disrespect, 1997; Series 2 (Box BOX 6, Folder 6)
  - Presidential Disrespect, 1997; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Marcus Raskin Speech on Nixon Tape, 1998; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Bahr Review Nation, 1999; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Biography with Spero, 1999; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Interview with Spero, 2000; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Reason and Reconstruction Levinee, 2002; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Iraq Questions, 2003; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Iraq, 2003; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Book Proposal, 2004; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Bush/Jackson, 2004; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - GW University Seminar, 2004; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Freedom From Want Conversations, 2004; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Strategy Questions, 2004; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Wisconsin Historical Society, 2004; Series 2 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - It's Your Freedom, 2004; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Reconstructive Knowledge, Undated; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Presidents - Summaries, Undated; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Paper for the Study of Progressive Liberalism, Undated; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Practice of Hope, Undated; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - New Paths Toward Peace and Disarmament, Undated; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - More on Visions and Revisions, Undated; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Affirmative action, Undated; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Marc's documents on hold, Undated; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - University of Moral Science, Undated; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Disarmament papers, Undated; Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous articles, Undated; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Housing, Undated; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Housing - 2, Undated; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Cuba, Undated; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Sign Up for War, Undated; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Paths: La Famiglia, Undated; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Paths Key Words, Undated; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Liberalism, Undated; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous writings, Undated; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous writings, Undated; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous writings, Undated; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Correspondence and personal papers, 1984-2009; Series 3
  This series contains correspondence to and from Marcus Raskin and some of Raskin's personal papers. The documents date between 1984-2009.
  - Marcus Raskin and Soviet Union (Photos), 1984-1985; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Bernstein correspondence Science New Physics, 1987; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1992; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1993; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Marc's 60th, 1994; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Marcus - correspondence, 1994; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1995; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Trachtenberg, 1995-1996; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Marcus Raskin correspondence, 1995; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Chomsky, 1996; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Letters to be answered, 1997-1998; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Personal letters, 1997-1999; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1999-2004; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Nader, 2000; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Cliburn, 2000; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Emails and designs, 2001-2004; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 2001-2008; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Writings, 2002-2009; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Hope, 2004; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Syllabus - Freedom and Security, 2004; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Letters, 2006-2009; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Marc's notes, Undated; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 14)